Every week I get at least three emails
from districts all over the state of California
looking for theater teachers.
It's a great time to be a theater teacher.
In order to get into
a credential program,
you need to meet the following requirements.
First, you need a bachelor's degree.
Second, you need to show
subject matter competency.
Subject matter competency simply means
that you know your stuff about theater.
This is because
a credential program doesn't
teach you what to teach,
it teaches you
how to teach what you know.
Most applicants already
have an undergraduate
or graduate theater degree,
which is all you need for
subject matter competency.
Most people who don't have subject matter competency
through a degree
go through a process called transcript evaluation.
This means that you complete a form and somebody -
at Cal State East Bay, me -
looks at your transcripts
and determines
if you have the knowledge
and skills to teach theater.
This almost always fulfills
subject matter competency,
especially if you have a theater or a drama minor.
If you don't have a degree,
you can always take the CSET exam.
Professional experience
and classes taken outside
of higher education
do not count towards
subject matter competency.
And although
many of our students
have lots of experience
working with kids,
teaching experience
is not a requirement
to get into the program.
Remember, it's our job
to teach you how to teach.
What is important
is that you have
the dispositions
to be a good teacher,
such as an understanding
of collaboration,
the habit of self-reflection,
the belief that all students
have the ability to learn.
The willingness to take on responsibilities
and a commitment to ongoing learning.